<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The innocent countrey-man's reflections, upon some emergent differences of late, and his seasonable advice to a divided people, in time of imminent danger silver and gold have I none to buy the medicins, but my advice I tender humbly without either of the two.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1386</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13069176</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13069176</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97093</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 742:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The innocent countrey-man's reflections, upon some emergent differences of late, and his seasonable advice to a divided people, in time of imminent danger silver and gold have I none to buy the medicins, but my advice I tender humbly without either of the two.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97093:1"/>
            <p>The INNOCENT COUNTREY-MAN'S REFLECTIONS, Upon ſome Emergent DIFFERENCES Of Late; and his Seaſonable ADVICE TO A DIVIDED PEOPLE, In time of Imminent Danger.</p>
            <p>Silver and Gold have I none to buy the Medicins, but my <hi>Advice I</hi> tender humbly without either of the two.</p>
            <q>Diabolus plerumque vult nocere, &amp; non poteſt, quia poteſtas illa ſub poteſtate; nam ſi tantum noceret Diabolus quantum vult, aliquis justorum non remaneret.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Super. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Deus eum (ſc. Diabolum) potentiae ſuae fraeno vinctum conſtrictumque tenet: ut ea modo exequatur quae ei Divinitus mandata aut conceſsa fuerint.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Piſcator</hi> exages: Aphor: <hi>14.</hi> pag. <hi>133.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Divines Explain, not without good ground, that by the Devil is not only underſtood in Holy Writ, theſe fallen Angels, which are chain'd up till God's permiſſion, from Afflicting the Juſt; But alſo his evil Inſtruments, who ſtand up, not only to Accuſe the Righteous, but alſo to Oppreſs and Perſecute them, in their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fame, Life, and Eſtate, and Retard all good Works and Indeavours, as Satan ſtood up againſt <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the high Prieſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <bibl>in <hi>Zechariah, cap.</hi> 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> May 1ſt. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97093:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97093:2"/>
            <head>The Countrey Man's Seaſonable Advice to a Divided People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe that trace the Reconcilers Paths, (were they at Variance never ſo near in Relation, Profeſſion, or Religion) or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily meet with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Treatment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. cap.</hi> 2, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13, 14, 15.</note> yet the Imbecillity, or Ingratitude of Men, ought not to be of any force, to drive the Rational Man from his Duty; though it occaſioned offence to the Peeviſh; as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid, <hi>Si de veritate ſcandalum ſumitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. de li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bero arbitrio.</note> 
               <hi>utilius permittitur naſci ſcandalum quam veritas relinquatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seing Sacred Writ pronounces a Bleſs to the Peace-maker: and one of the Moral Phyloſophers could ſay, <hi>Optimum eſt quod in praeſentia oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit bene agere.</hi> Yea moſt of the Moral Philoſophers, did not only ſuggeſt, but inculcat theſe Divine Principles of Union and Concord to their Schollars,<note n="*" place="margin">Alexander in Pythag: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</note> 
               <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium quidem omnium unitas eſt, ex qua indefinitam dualitatem, veluti materiam autori unitate ſubjeciſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Heathen <hi>Maxims</hi> and <hi>Aphoriſms,</hi> yea, their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices may make Chriſtians aſhamed, when they reflect upon theirs; much more may thoſe who profeſs the Proteſtant Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be aſhamed, who ſell their nobleſt Paſſions of Love, to that of Prejudice and Hatred; Peace and Union, to that of Diſcord and Malice, <hi>for a meſs of pottage;</hi> This is no Sacred Hunger, but rather reſembles the Dog in the Fables, <hi>Who lost a ſweet Morſel to piccaroun a Shadow;</hi> and are ſuch, who <hi>neglect the greater matters of the Law, to catch Flies;</hi> Or who <hi>Gallio</hi> like, are too indifferent, or look more to the <hi>Letter of the Law, than Fundamentals:</hi> Thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying that ſweet Union, Communion and Concord ought to be among them of the ſame Religion and Profeſſion, not ſeriouſly conſidering, that Violence can never accompliſh the true, or right ends of agreeable things deſired, or to be hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And it could be wiſhed, that by theſe Methods (to our ſad experience, if we believe Preſidents of undoubted Truth, might quadrat with our caſe) we give not too much advantage to the common Enemy, if not the Enemy of Mankind it ſelf (compoſed of Popiſh Emiſſaries, and lax or wavering Proteſtants) who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Divine Maxim, <hi>make gain their godlineſs,</hi> and deſign downright to divide honeſt, well-meaning men in their Sentiments, by improving <hi>Matchiavils</hi> Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; impera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though linked together for bad deſigns, yet being of different complexions and conditions, may meet with diſappointments, when they come to a Point they muſt of neceſſity differ in, if the one party propoſes any good end, the other does not, <hi>&amp; caveant ne inter loquendum ſecreta pronuncient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All good men, though of different Sentiments and Opinions, (were their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions the ſame) will be ready to ſay (whether true or falſe, none can be Judge, but each particular man of his own Intentions and Actions, when not done in the face of the Sun) that they have the right end of the Staff, that they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain none in their Society but good men, ſuch as are for the common Good, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace and Safety, Settling the Government in unqueſtionable Hands, and are for the King's true Service, and the welfare of the Countrey in general, <hi>ſo be it:</hi> And I know this is indeed <hi>Lully's Aurum potabile vulgi, ſed veritas non latet angulis, neque conjunctione maledicis, anguinis aut maleficis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make theſe Aſſertions clear by Evidences, ſeing <hi>the Tree is known by the Fruit,</hi> baniſh Peeviſhneſs, and let private Intereſt, which is too obvious, be laid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97093:3"/>aſide; for as there is no agreement betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mammon,</hi> nor communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> well-meaning men, and evil deſigning men, (where <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia familiaritas demum parit contemptum</hi>) ſo well-meaning men will drive to the liklieſt and ſafeſt Harbour of the two, ſince the Ship muſt inevitably periſh, if it drive into the one, and ſhun the other; for we have a very Pathetick <hi>Scots Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm,</hi> tho it may ſeem Ruſtick, <hi>Such man as thou would be, draw thee to ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whether it be ſafer to drive the Ship, (toſſed by violent Storms in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful Surges, granting all that is alledged) on a Sandy Shore, or upon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Rock, when either muſt be, let rational men Judge, <hi>cum melius inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet in theſe particulars, when men are their own Judges, the beſt are apt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge their Senſes and Fancies, and without Examination, decide in their own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; when upon a reference to indifferent Judges, the Queſtion might decide more equally, to the ſatisfaction of both parties; If men permit not their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be impoſed upon, with their ignobler Paſſions and Frailties, leaning too much thitherwards, as <hi>Sulla</hi> did, by reſigning the abſolute power of his Dictator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which he took upon him for a longer time than his Life, of whom <hi>Julius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> ſaid <hi>Ironicè, quia neſciverit dictare (intelligitur ambignus) quod munus eſt Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matici,</hi> meaning, that Grammarians had a kind of an abſolute power to indict Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts to their Schollars, <hi>unde videtur dictator;</hi> and no doubt, men endowed with Senſe &amp; Reaſon, &amp; pretending to Honour, ought to give Precepts (as <hi>Seneca and Socrates</hi> did) the reſtraining of all their Luſts, Paſſions, and Infirmities, for the common pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt and Peace's ſake, and when men are maſters of their Reaſons, as well as their Infirmities (though differing in Sentiments, and reflecting but a little ſeriouſly) they would readily admit of indifferent Judges, by which the common Law, and Reaſon would become Rules to both. And if the Queſtion, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie were fairly and calmly ſtated, whether to be adequated to, or judged by the Precepts of the Law of Nature, poſitive Laws of God (revealed,) or poſitive Laws of Men, (as adapted to both the former, and enacted, agreeable to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of reſpective Societies, and Common-wealths of rational men) every Point might have a definitive Sentence, to ſatisfie all unbyaſſed parties. And as the Learned Phyſicians of any experience, will not allow an <hi>Epoche</hi> in any Diſeaſe but Death. So our Nation, (which has its <hi>Era's</hi> of all agreeable things inferior to no other) muſt not be banter'd with the reflection of having educat of late, but one, or few or more <hi>Parmenis's,</hi> (whoſe Counſels would have the eſteem of Oracles) to heal all our Breaches their own way only.</p>
            <p>But ſome men will ſay, granting all this, yet that ſuch and ſuch particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have been deſtructive to the very Laudable Conſtitutions of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or miſchievous, or evil Inſtruments in the former Governments, ought not to be truſted (after a happy Revolution) in a Healing and Good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. To this I agree, but at the ſame time Conſider well, and mark theſe that embrace them, <hi>neque id conſider andum quod dixerit, ſed utrum vere dicatur necne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato.</note> ſo that I am not to be Judged by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny byaſſed man, more than he is to be by me; and at leaſt there ought to be a fair Tryal in the caſe, unleſs we be too unequally ſtated; for though I be innocent, and my neighbours ſeem to be guilty, without a fair Tryal and Proof, the Ballance betwixt us is not cleared, <hi>non peccantes modo, verum &amp; peccare geſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes punito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So ſtill Reaſon and Law muſt decide the Controverſie: Theſe that pretend innocence; if innocent, no doubt are more to be truſted than the faulty, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when the former are of equal capacity; Yet in our preſent Accuſations (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from attrocious Crimes, and perſons guilty of them, who are not vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated) we may interpoſe our Saviour's anſwer to the Phariſees, concerning the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man taken in Adultery, that <hi>he who is not a ſinner ſhould throw the firſt ſtone;</hi> In
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97093:3"/>which caſe, I doubt much who would have the confidence to make the firſt attempt. If we make a ſcrutiny into the <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> of Moraliſts, in reference to all Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governments, and inflicting of puniſhments for Crimes, (laying aſide Threed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare Reflections), we would find very moderat Preſcripts, and Preſidents: For <hi>Periander</hi> could ſay, <hi>qui tuto regnare vellent, ſumma ope nitendum, ut benevolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non armis stiparentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Pittacus</hi> (which may meet with our Caſe very appoſitely) ſaid, <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum imperium eſt victorias ſine ſanguine acquiri.</hi> And we find in Sacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit, that the beſt had not only their faults and failings, but were likewiſe guilty of the groſſeſt Enormities; <hi>Moſes</hi> offended in his paſſion, for which he was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of entering into the <hi>promiſed Land,</hi> yet a Saint, and a Type of our Saviour's Humane Perſon: <hi>David</hi> a great Sinner yea, a Tranſgreſſor, in acting contrair to the known Laws of the Land, indicted by the Spirit of God, particularly in <hi>eating the ſhew-bread, and numbring of the people,</hi> for which they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, yet he declared to be <hi>a man according to God's own heart: Hezekiah</hi> ſinned, in expoſing his Wealth and Treaſure, (out of Oftentation to the Uncircumciſed) yet Repenting, ſound Mercy, and obtained his deſire: <hi>Manaſseh</hi> Sinned much more, but upon his Repentance obtained pardon: <hi>Peter</hi> and the Thief upon the Croſs, are notorious examples of their ſins, and mercies upon their Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>By all which we may perceive, that God does not in time Deſtroy, or eternally Damn men for every particular failing, and ſin, provided they Repent; But he exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes his Wrath for a continued tract of ſin, unrepented of; a wilful denyal, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring of the Truth, and breaking of his expreſs Command, where he declares his unalterable juſt Judgment for the breach thereof, <hi>or lying to the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such were the Caſes of <hi>Balaam, Achan, Judas, Annanias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> whoſe Sins being extraordinary, met with the like Puniſhment; And in all Civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths and Societies of Men, the rigour of the Law is never put in execution for each perſons Offence therein, but are mitigated; one Reaſon thereof is very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, becauſe Laws are made <hi>magis ad terrorem quam executionem;</hi> for if Mens Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were not ſo much depraved, the Precepts of the Law of Nature, and the Dictates of Mens own Conſciences might be Rules of Humane Actions and Manners: But by reaſon of our pravitie, Poſitive Laws are made to keep us in awe, and to put us in mind of our Dutie in relation to God, our Neighbours and our ſelves, Superiours, Inferiours and Equals, to chaſtiſe Men as a Penalty for Diſobedience, and not to deſtroy them for Failings of every kind; and the more we imitate God, in reference to his Juſtice and Mercy, the better: for the extremity of Mercy is more ſafe, than the extremity of Juſtice, or the rigour of the Law: Not that I think it is the prudence of ſafety of any Society or Common-wealth, to let all Tranſgreſſors paſs unpuniſhed, provided that Men that would inflict the Puniſhment be not guilty of the ſame, the like, or greater Faults or Crimes, <hi>Nam optime &amp; juſtiſſime vivere eſt, ſi quae in aliis reprehendimus ipſi non faciamus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thales, Mileſius.</note> And it is confeſt that the letting all Tranſgreſſors go free would be a ready way to ſhake the very Foundations and Conſtitutions of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yea the very ends of their linking together in a body Politick: But ſo (as in an happie Revolution) theſe having the Legiſlative or Executive Power, would put the Law moderatly in execution, without Paſſion, Perſonal Prejudice, By aſs or any evil Deſign; yea that upon a general Jealouſie of Men, theſe whoſe inclinations or endeavours have been or may be prejudicial, or deſtructive to the Common-wealth, may be made incapable to temporize, or act any thing tending to the overthrow of the Government; and that perſons guilty of attrocious Crimes, might be animadverted upon by way of moderat Juſtice: for as the beſt blood makes the beſt temperament of Humane
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97093:4"/>Bodies; ſo in a Body Politick, the beſt Humors and Conditions of Men makes the beſt Temperament of Government, <hi>for Vengeance is mine, (ſaith the Lord) and I will repay it.</hi> And God forbid, this good Government ſhould be tainted with the ſame Inhumane, Unchriſtian-Cruelties and Oppreſſions towards perſons of different Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents and Profeſſions the later Governments were guilty of, for which they do ly under an heavy Charge; ſo let us never run to the ſame Extravagances we complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in other Men.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, That that Government is but in a tottering condition, when in ſuch a critical Juncture, ſuch as are not only guilty of attrocious Crimes, but even theſe who labour generally under a bad Suſpition, and are obnoxious to the People, ſhould not only be ſheltered under the Government, but be alſo introduced into places of greateſt Truſt, and that the People ſhould not be rid of all thoſe creeping Evils, as <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> put away his Wife, becauſe he thought that all theſe of his Houſe ought to be clear of all Suſpitions as well as Crimes: And as <hi>Octavius Ceſar uti Pater Patriae,</hi> obtained a Decree of the Senat, to compell eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gentleman [who ſerved with the Cities Horſe] to render an account of his Life; granting all this, yet at the ſame time <hi>Octavius</hi> made a diſtinction of Crimes and Puniſhments; for ſuch as were blameable, and could not approve their Actions, ſome he Puniſhed, others he noted with Shame and Ignominy, but the moſt part of them with Admonitions, and tendering of the <hi>Tables</hi> in open places, where all their Faults were written: And it could be wiſh'd that theſe or ſuch like were our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Healing the Diſtempers of the State, for it were hard [in a gentle, well governed State] to proſtitute Authority to every privat man's opinion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to unhinge the Bands thereof: This were to make a Government, like that fine piece of Painting, which the Painter thereof expoſed to every Paſſengers view, and tho every Spectator applauded it to be the fineſt done Picture in the World, yet all found ſome particular Fault to it, and the Painter by pleaſing every man's Fancy in mending it, the Picture at laſt look'd like a Monſter of Nature; and a wiſe, good and Politick Governour could ſay, <hi>Nam ſponte &amp; invitum cedere aeque periculoſum eſt;</hi> and in the twelve <hi>Roman Tables,</hi> none was to loſe his place, or to be condemned to die, but upon full Proof by the Sentence of the General Aſſembly; and in the <hi>Romans Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> after Healing of the Cauſe with great Deliberation, the Judge delivered the <hi>Tabella,</hi> where was written, C, A, N, L, ſignifying, <hi>Condemnation, Abſolution,</hi> and <hi>Non Liquets,</hi> Indicating that the Cauſe of any Man was to be Heard over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again, and not raſhly to be Condemn'd, placing <hi>Probatioplena</hi> to be the ground of a juſt Sentence, and not <hi>Fama clamoſae; nam facile eſt reprehendere &amp; maledicere:</hi> And the <hi>Grecians</hi> had Letters alſo to expreſs their Sentences, Θ Τ Α, which were to the ſame purpoſe: And the <hi>Romans</hi> had different Puniſhments, <hi>viz. mulctam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premam, mulctam minimam,</hi> as well as <hi>capitis diminutionem;</hi> and theſe had their Subdiſtinctions alſo, but were always tender of the <hi>Patrician</hi> Order or Degree, yea Criminal Judges have White in their Robes as well as Red for a Badge of Mercy as well as Juſtice. Wiſdom wont to be painted as a beautiful Woman, with four Ears and four Hands, but with one Tongue, and no Arms of Cruelty. The <hi>Dolphin</hi> obtained the Honour to ſignifie the King or Emperor of the Seas, becauſe it's ſaid to be kind, gentle and grateful; and ſhall not Men, endowed with Senſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Profeſſing Chriſtianity, yea Proteſtants, take example of the Heathens; Pagans, or the Bruits, but rather reſemble the <hi>Salamander,</hi> who by reaſon of its unkindly moiſt Conſtitution, labours in the Fire, but when out of it, leaves ſome impreſſion upon the very Fruits of the Earth of its cold and poyſonous nature; or like the <hi>Hydra,</hi> the Hyrogliphick of envious Souls. Let us rather reſemble the Sun and its beautiful Beams, repreſenting the Unity, Wiſdom, Concord and Love ought to be amongſt thoſe linked together in a Common wealth or Society, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean towards one another, as the kindly and naturally affectioned Dragon, who cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97093:4"/>his fellow Creatures Malady, by tendring him an Herb, which taught the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Polyidus</hi> by the ſame Cure to raiſe <hi>Glaucus</hi> from death to his Fathers joy.</p>
            <p>But not to conſume too much time on that which God and Nature muſt work upon perſons who are inexorable, [or who are in Paroxiſms, if I may ſpeak ſo with grief,] more than Examples, Preſidents, Precepts or Counſels, though all were Oracles, [which brings me in remembrance of that antient Maxim, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by <hi>Valerius,</hi> in relation to Mens greateſt Difficulties,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum noſcere difficile.</hi>] I come to particulars, of which I will treat but very briefly, and in more general terms, that no honeſt man of what Party, Opinion or Sentiment whatſoever ſhall have reaſon to take exception. Then,</p>
            <p>When the Regal Power was devolved upon their preſent Majeſties, [whom the Heavens were pleaſed, with the Counſel and Aſſiſtance of ſome honeſt Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to make glorious Inſtruments to relieve us from Arbitrary and Deſpotick Power, Popery and Slavery, and our fears of more Miſcheif,] the three Eſtates did then give ſo much deference to, and put ſo much confidence in their Majeſties [of which I am hopeful we need never to repent] That the three Eſtates of the Nation then Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, did chearfully and unanimouſly devolve the ſame, and offered the Crown with an Inſtrument of Government, and a Petition, with a Claim of Right, for Redreſs of Grievances: All, as was then judged, [if there were no omiſſions <hi>medio tempore; nam humanum eſt tam omittere quam errare</hi>] bounded within the compaſs of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Articles, which their Majeſties promiſed to perform, provided that ſome of theſe Articles did not bind them up ſo, as to force them to be perſecuters of men for their Religion, or Opinion, in matters of Conſcience only; which was an expreſs <hi>Salvo.</hi> And what was further underſtood then by ſome men, but what was materially Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed in Form by theſe Articles, if Literal, is a Riddle; For certainly, by their Literal Senſe, the King and His Adviſers can eaſily be exonered from any unreaſonable Reflections can be put upon them, for any alteration appears as yet; And if there be more meant than is expreſſed in theſe Articles, and Claim, as formed, there is no rational good man will charge His Majeſty with an Obligation of performing ſuch things he knew not were deſired and underſtood, yet not expreſt; For it muſt be a Divine Beeing muſt know mens thoughts, frail men know only the Actions and Expreſſions of Men: And it is look'd upon to be one of the moſt firm Maxims amongſt School men, that <hi>Immateriale non agit in materiale, niſi eminenter, ut</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: So that Divinity muſt only have Preſcience.</p>
            <p>And, as God forbid we ſhould be guilty of miſtruſting ſuch a Wiſe, Juſt, and Couragious Prince, who did ſo much for us; ſo it's hoped we will never offer to impoſe more upon him, than what tends to our eaſe, ſecuring of our Civil and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rights, tending to the common Safety, Peace and Tranquillity of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general; in which no doubt all honeſt Countrey men will be equally concerned. And I am perſwaded, no Subject of any Degree will be more ready to contribute to the accompliſhment of theſe happy ends, than our Great and Gracious King, who was never known to have belyed his word, and who moſt frequently diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this Common Head, expreſſed himſelf thus, <hi>I deſire not to retain, or ask any thing from my People, but what may enable me in the Government, which they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved upon me, to ſecure their Religious and Civil Rights, and to protect them against theirs and my enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which gracious condeſcenſions of His Majeſties, makes me imagine, ere whiles I hear him in his Solitude expreſs himſelf thus with the great <hi>Octavius Caeſar Augustus,</hi> who had the Epithet, of <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sweton. de vita Octavii Caeſ. Aug.</note> 
               <q>Oh that I might eſtabliſh the Commonwealth ſafe and ſound upon their own proper Piedſtal (or Baſis) and thereof reap that fruit which I deſire, even that I may be reported the Author of an excellent Eſtate, and carry with me when I die this hope, that the Ground-work of the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97093:5"/>of the Common-wealth which I ſhall lay, may continue and abide ſtedfaſt in their place for ever after me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And what Prince in the World lived more happily and ſplendidly than His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, when Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> was he not the Darling of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the deſirable Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of all his good Neighbouring Princes, a Patron of Virtue, Piety and Frugality, a Protector of all diſtreſſed and perſecuted People, (of which many of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men are notorious evidences) the terrour of all deſigning men of evil Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and the dread of the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant, whoſe Activity and Proweſs he was more afraid of than all the Antichriſtian Bulls and Excommunications, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver too much lifted up, nor dejected, <hi>ſed ſemper inter ſecundas res moderatus, inter adver ſas prudens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid then we ſhould make his precious life uneaſie to him, (whom we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to come, and who came over for our relief) by our ingratitude, diviſions, and murmurings: For it is well known, that his method is to try ere he truſt, and where he finds capacity and honeſty, he never forſakes; which verifies that ſage Precept of <hi>Solon</hi>'s in him, <hi>Be not haſty making thy friend, and keep him when ye gain him;</hi> which two Rules <hi>Propertius</hi> elegantly comprehends in one Verſe,</p>
            <q>amare. Nec cito deſisto, nec temere incipie.</q>
            <p>Now if His Majeſty hath made, or will make ſuch Conceſſions, by the grant of His Royal Aſſent to ſuch Acts to be paſt in Parliament (without our running to heats, <hi>Jehu</hi>-like, to be guilty of cruelty by pretence of a Divine Call, by violence to deſtroy one another) as may anſwer our expectations, in relation to thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles for redreſs of Grievances; on whom ſhall we lay the heavy charge of not redreſſing other Grievances (were then but <hi>Embrio's</hi> at beſt) not mentioned in the Claim of Right: For I am perſwaded, if we had deſired more, as conditions at the devolving of the Government upon Their Majeſties, (before it had been done, if reaſonable) they had been granted. Sure I am we cannot blame Him or His Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for not giving Inſtructions concerning theſe things he knew not then to be Grievances; and if we run to the ignorant <hi>Mobile</hi>'s ſenſe of things, we'll find that they are like Melancholly perſons fancies, who fear things not to be feared, and to feign <hi>quae nec picta uſquam, nec ſcripta;</hi> like that <hi>Plebeian,</hi> who imagined that his Noſe was grown ſo great, that he durſt not go abroad, for fear it ſhould be hurt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or like the famous Poet at <hi>Amſterdame</hi> believed that his Buttocks were of Glaſs, <hi>&amp;c. Thomas Bartholinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent. Leg.</hi> 1.79. <hi>page</hi> 117.</note> 
               <hi>Fred.</hi> 3d King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>'s Phyſitian, ſo many people are abuſed by Dreams, Fancies and Tradition, and Hear-ſay, as I think Witch-craft and Popery go by Tradition or Relation. Have we not a clear demonſtration of His Majeſties Goodneſs and Condeſcendence in His Inſtructions (where beſide the redreſſing of thoſe Grievances, digeſted into ſo many Articles) by which he deſired to be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from time to time with any motion ſhould be made in Parliament, tending to the welfare of the Countrey and People, and he ſhould give his Inſtructions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Which Inſtruction ſeemed to Strangers, who were not verſant in our Forms, Cuſtoms and Laws, to be <hi>conceſsa ultra p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tila,</hi> to ſay no farther.</p>
            <p>God forbid I ſhould be guilty of charging my man, or men, with the neglect of proſecuting His Majeſties and Parliaments good deſign, tho Enemies and deſigning Men do take their advantage by breeding of Jealouſies, and creating of Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces amongſt honeſt men, for their own bad ends, and would ſeem to lay the charge either upon thoſe worthy Inſtruments, who contribute their advice to, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured their lives with the King in His firſt Enterprize, (which in all healing Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be eſteemed full expiations of perſons faults, though guilty) or others, who were the greateſt Props in theſe perillous critical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es: And the moſt active to promove, and to bring to a happy concluſion the great Work then acted upon the Stage: And for which they not only deſerve the Lawrels of praiſe, but alſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97093:5"/>and Rewards, as ſuitable returns, <hi>ſed hec Deus juſſit, non dii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am apt to impute our <hi>nigrum vulnus</hi> of diviſions and too much heat, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended diſaſters from the common enemy, to Fatality and God's permiſſion: <hi>For is there any evil comes upon the City that is not of the Lord,</hi> that is, by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? more than from any apprehenſion I have of a conjunction of thoſe different Perſwaſions, and of different propoſed ends: For I cannot be driven to range in a Field of Diffidence towards honeſt men, who not only mean well, but were conſiderable Actors of a happy Scene in the late Revolution. Nor can I once ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine worthy Patriots will be guilty of being impoſed upon by bad men to break the Bond of Peace, ought to be (like the Guardian Knot) amongſt honeſt well-Principled Men, that have the ſame propoſed good ends after a happy Revolution in a healing time. And if we were ſo happy as to lay aſide all thoſe perſonal Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, Pieques, Heats, Animoſities and Emulation incident to Humane Frailty (maugre all evil Inſtruments) and in cold Blood weigh our duty to God, to our Benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Neighbours, and our ſelves, our holy Religion and Profeſſion, and the ſame and ſecurity we owe to our Poſterity, more than particular intereſt, and worldly gain, we needed not be afraid with evil Aſpects, or frightful Viſions of the Enemys, Bandying together for our common deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The great work then in hand (to the concerting and accompliſhing of which, I pray the Heavens may be propitious to us for a happy iſſue) is, that all good well-deſigning men, (who have nothing more before their eyes than the glory of God, the King's honour, the common good, the advancement of our holy Religion, and the general peace and tranquillity of the Nation) joyn together with heart and hand, (not <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſseh,</hi> and <hi>Manaſseh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> but both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Amalek,</hi> and all the uncircumciſed) and bring Materials with them to heal the breaches of our Walls where they are weakeſt, broken and expoſed, too obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the enemies watchful eye and inſolence, whoſe bands are ſtrong, but not to be made ſtronger by our joyning with them. And to the end that our gracious King may be the more and more encouraged to grant all our juſt deſires, (ſo as we may not look upon him to be ſuch a Father as would give us a Scorpion for a Fiſh, which if we do, we are unhappy.) Let us in the firſt place aſſiſt and enable him to make good to us, what we our ſelves in a manner obliged him to perform, <hi>viz.</hi> the Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances contained in theſe Articles, and I doubt not but all our juſt emergent Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances will be concerted to a general ſatisfaction, which will March up in the Rere, and in its due time will joyn with the Van-guard, and both will prove one Brazen Wall, which I hope the common Enemy will never be able to come over again.</p>
            <p>This would be the method to make King and People, Nobility, Gentry and Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant happy; for by joyning together, the common enemy their expectations would fail, <hi>nam ſapiens dominabitur aſtris.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paracelſ.</note> But if we offer to take an evil Party by the hand, to heal thoſe breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es (which they themſelves made in the Hedges of our Religious and Civil Rights) they will prove Eels in our hands, yea bitter in the digeſtion, ſince their Concoction had no good foundation; our true or pretended ſufferings will be forgotten, we'll loſe our reputation we bore of Religion, Profeſſion and Virtue, and all good men will ſuſpect our Principles and Ingenuity, yet God will proſper his own Work begun, and it will be made evident to the World we have no hand in it. For we muſt not only apply <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s Meſſage to <hi>Eſther, Cap</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13, and 14. to any particular perſon in the State, but to all good men in the State in their ſeveral capacities, to put to their hand to heal the breaches of the State and Church. But for all that is paſt, <hi>oblivioni tradita eſto;</hi> and all good men expect good things of us as yet, for all the great Heats, Animoſities, and Conteſts about trifles.</p>
            <p>Then as ye love the Intereſt of God, your Religion, your King and Countrey, and as ye tender a reſpect to the intereſt of Proteſtants at home and abroad, all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97093:6"/>whoſe eyes are upon you, <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men,</hi> proceed regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ingeniouſly, follow a ſolid method to ſettle State and Church.</p>
            <p>And after ye have accommodated your Preliminaries, and conſtituted the Houſe in its Members, Priviledges, and Committees, proſecute the great work in hand.</p>
            <p>And the firſt particular breach in our Walls ought to be repaired, is, the ſettling of the Church-government now without Form: In Concerting and Eſtabliſhing of which, I will not offer to preſcribe Rules, ſubmitting that to the determination (by the Divine Aſſiſtance, with the Advice of a Moderate and Learned Miniſtry) of ſuch a Learned, Sage Parliament, as this is; but wiſhes it may be ſo Concerted, as moſt agreeable to the Word of God, and general inclination of the People; ſo as the Secular and Eccleſiaſtical Intereſts may not interfier, or prove troubleſome to one another, after the ſettlement, each knowing their own Diſtricts, and acting their part, and going about their particular Duties and Callings, in their reſpective Spheres, without intermedling in others bounds. Yet <hi>I</hi> preſume, that ſuch an Honourable, Wiſe and Religious Parliament, as this is, will Eſtabliſh that Church Government, which is moſt agreeable to the Genious of the People of tendereſt Conſciences, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it be conſonant to the word of God; for the Church Governments, which were Eſtabliſhed by Law in <hi>Scotland,,</hi> were only two; and no doubt, that part of the People, who make Church Government a conſcientious principle, for which they could ſuffer in both their Fortunes and Lives, ought rather to be pleaſed (giving and not granting, that both were equally ſtated) than the other, who make both a matter indifferent, and could with a ſafe conſcience (or once hazard of the leaſt ſuffering in either) joyn in diſciplin and worſhip with the former, when as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cannot joyn with them in either of the two.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is for you own Security, that ye cordially and unanimouſly, and ſuddenly, if at all, grant ſuch a Supply to Their Majeſties, as may not only pay the Army their bygone Arrears, to ſatisfie the poor Countrey people, to whom they are much indebted, and to Re-imburſe the ſeveral Officers who have been at vaſt Charges to ſerve the Publick: But alſo to make it ſuch a Supply, as may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to maintain a competent number of Forces on Foot, for a certain time, as will be ſufficient to Reduce the Rebellious <hi>Highlanders,</hi> and Defend the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from Forraign Invaſion, in this dangerous Conjuncture, (when we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt, whether many in our very Boſoms be Friends, or Foes;) for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a conſiderable Fond, we cannot expect that the Forces can be kept together, and yet without them, we are in no Security of our Lives or Fortunes, nor are we, I hope, of that Perſwaſion, as to expect our Victory, or Safety from Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</p>
            <p>It will be Objected, that we want Trade, and that the Land is not able to bear a great Supply, (by reaſon of our frequent Haraſſes, and general Devaſtations,) as will be ſufficient to ſupport an Army for any conſiderable time; Both may be true, yet <hi>Neceſſity hath no Law,</hi> but we muſt reſolve to give part voluntarly to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us, or to be Deſtroyed Root and Branch, (and both Moities will periſh like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) if the Supply be not granted; and me thinks, there is no difficulty to make ſuch a Fond, for if Trade and the Land be not able to undergo the Burden, why may not the Taxes to be laid upon the Land and Trade, be made eaſie, by Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an equal Poll upon all perſons according to their Eſtate and Degree, after the Laudable Cuſtom of our Neighbouring Nation, and that Money bear its Burden alſo, (which was ſeldom or never Taxed) with due reſpect always to mens deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Sums and Debt, whoſe Stock conſiſts in Moveables only; ſo that all perſons under the Protection of the Government, will contribute ſomething, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions will be unſenſible to all, if the Regulation and Ingathering be truſted in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable, honeſt, and unqueſtionable Hands.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97093:6"/>There is one great neglect, which it's wiſht might be remeided (humbly Repreſented to the Honourable Parliament) would contribute much to advance, and inrich the generality of people in this Nation, to the enabling of them to bear Burden in ſuch Exigencies, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Product of the Countrey, by an Act, ſhould be ſold at greater Rates; for by the great price given for Forraign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities Imported (many of which are more for the Fancy and Pallat, than the Intrinſick Value, Profit, or neceſſity of bringing them home;) and the mean prices of the Countrey Product, (Retailed at Home, or Exported Abroad,) the Nobility and Gentry are not only at a great loſs, but the poor Farmers are Drudges and Slaves to particular people, and it may be rationally concluded; that they are but particular perſons in every corner of the Nation, who exhale and drain the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (to whom the Civil Law did give but little truſt, or incouragement, who by their kind of Frugality, whether Juſt, or Unjuſt, it's eaſily Divin'd) become rich on a ſudden, and keeps the Body of the Nation, who undergoes all the Burden, low, and the Commonality in Bondage.</p>
            <p>I deſire to be excuſed for this Digreſſion, but the wiſeſt of men are not one whit the worſe; nor does it derogat, to be put in mind of a Duty, or convenience, e're whiles, — <hi>Nam gutta cavat lapidem non vi ſed ſaepe cadendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Particular, is the Reducing of honeſt mens Forfeitures, whoſe Eſtates and Fortunes (in the later Reigns) for their firm adherence to the Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and for Conſcience ſake, were violently taken from them by ſtretches of Law, and what elſe I know not; and the ſudden Reſtoring of theſe Noblemen and Gentlemen to their Juſt Rights, Eſtates, and Fortunes, will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enable them to joyn with their Councils and Intereſts, to ſerve the Government, and to Support the neceſſary Burdens thereof in its exigencies, but will alſo diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage a Malevolent, Reſtleſs Party, who go about in Sheeps Cloathing, ſo far as is poſſible to deceive the honeſt Party.</p>
            <p>The fourth particular is, That there be Reſtitution made of all unjuſt Fines and Loſſes of honeſt people, who ſuffered for Conſcience ſake only, that they may put to their helping hand to Support the Government. I will not preſcribe Rules in this matter, Judging that honeſt people will be ſatisfied with the equivalent; but we find, that both the Moral, and Roman Law, have preſcribed excellent Rules con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Reſtitutions.</p>
            <p>A fifth particular, with humble ſubmiſſion to the wiſe Parliament's better Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Burrows Rights and Grievances would be conſidered; for it ſeems to be very hard, that the Burrows ſhall bear the ſixth part of publick Burden of the Nation, and Unfree Corporations ſhould inhaunce the very Subſtance of Trade, yet bear no Burden for it.</p>
            <p>We might have Treated upon all the reſt of the Grievances, without giving of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to any, but judges theſe to be ſufficient for one days work.</p>
            <p>And theſe being the firſt, and moſt neceſſary Grievances to be ſpeedily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt, the reſt will follow in conſequence, whether they be conditioned to us, or come emergently under our view, and accounted as <hi>Remora's</hi> in our way to Peace, Tranquillity, and Temporary Happineſs.</p>
            <p>It will be Objected, that when theſe Points, which we are all willing ſhould be firſt and principally concerted, are paſt into Laws, we may be diſappointed of the others, though als neceſſary, by Adjourning, or Diſſolving the Parliament before Redreſs, and therefore not fit to lay down the Cudgels againſt our common, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Enemies, who are the diſturbers of the publick Peace, till firſt we get theſe Grievances Redreſt, which concern our Rights, Liberties and Priviledges, as well as the other, or have full aſſurance of Redreſſing all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Anſwer firſt, That <hi>de poſse ad eſse non valet argumentum;</hi> but taking up the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in the Complex, <hi>I</hi> Anſwer, Secondly, Though I be als much for contribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97093:7"/>my Mite, to have all juſt Grievances, publick and privat Redreſt as any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and perhaps hath been as actively concerned therein, <hi>pro rata,</hi> as others preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more; yet at the ſame time <hi>I</hi> cannot be driven from the Opinion, to think that it were ſpliting upon the dangerous, inevitable Rocks of <hi>Scylla,</hi> or <hi>Charybdis,</hi> to miſtruſt our Gracious King of His Word and Promiſe, conſidering His natural and known Integrity, and Ingenuity, who aſſures us of the Redreſſing of all our juſt Grievances, and is ſtill ready to make all reaſonable Conceſſions. Or (though we had other thoughts of Him, or His Miniſters, as God forbid) that we ſhould ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the common Safety, &amp; let the Publick ſuffer, by hindring the Settlement of the <hi>quid maxime neceſſarium,</hi> if we obtained not all our Deſires in one moment of time; or that for a ſmall delay in the one, we ſhould be ſo wilful, or unfortunat, as to retard the other, eſpecially when <hi>I</hi> do not in the leaſt doubt, if we put on the Armour of Patience againſt our own precipitant temper, but by Peice-meal we might procure all our Deſires, and in common Diſcourſe, we uſe to ſay, <hi>That</hi> Rome <hi>was not built in one day:</hi> The <hi>Venetians,</hi> who are accounted the moſt Politick, and Trimming Common-wealth in <hi>Europe,</hi> have a <hi>Proverb, He that walketh ſlowly, walketh more ſecurely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the frequent Adjournments of this Current Parliament, ſince the laſt Sederunt, there were ſeveral Reaſons of State for it, als well as for our good, not fit to be expoſed to every man's particular view, in ſuch a critical, prying Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, may afterwards be made appear, to a general ſatisfaction, if needful, and abſtracting from what ſatisfaction could be truly given on this head; all rational men will conclude, that ſometimes delays are more agreeable, and ſafe in many caſes, weighing circumſtances of people, time and place, than too much precipitancy; ſo that as <hi>Ennius</hi> ſaid, <hi>In commend Qu:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus homo nobis cunctando reſtituit rem.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I hope it may be verified in our Gracious Prince, and His Council, Miniſters in this caſe. Engliſhed thus,</p>
            <q>
               <l>One man alone by ſage delay,</l>
               <l>Reſtor'd our State fall'n to decay.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And did Our Gracious King Judge't expedient upon ſome emergent occaſions to Adjourn for a longer time, (as it's hoped there is not, nor ſhall be reaſon for it) I'm perſwaded there would be ſatisfactory Reaſons given to the rational, moderat, and well affected to the Government, in its due time for the accident.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps may ſay, they have run ſo far, that they can't in Conſcience, or at leaſt in Honour, Retrive without a Golden Apple: I ſhould be ſorry to think that by miſapplication, Conſcience, or Honour ſhould be Diſlodged, their proper Domicils, that Candidats for want of Illuminations, ſhould miſtake, or miſs the Prize-Stake, where either of the two, or both may be placed, and wead in a Flood, to gain them at a Stake, where none of the three are fixed; or ſhould make uſe of obſcurer Inſtruments, where more proper ones are at hand, to clear Difficulties, or Doubts, like the man that made uſe of a Lanthorn to know the Hour in clear Day Light. The Wiſe ale ever aſhamed to relinquiſh, or baniſh an Error, be it hidden or conſpicuous, if the faillure tend to the prejudice of the publick, or privat In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: For as a great Father ſaid, <hi>Expedit bene timere quam male fidere, &amp; melius eſt ut infirmus ſe homo agnoſcat, ut fortis existat quam fortis videri velit, &amp; infirmus emergat. Atque errare humanum eſt. ſed in errore perſeverare belluinum ac Diabolicum est.</hi> But if rational men will perpetrat in their miſtakes, (not that I charge particular perſons with any further than what is very incident to the greateſt mens humane frailties) <hi>maxime periculoſum, eſt,</hi> I lay may hand upon my mouth, and crave
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97093:7"/>their pardon, if <hi>I</hi> have been officious, <hi>A Fool's Bolt being ſoon ſhot,</hi> ſo may mine: Yet at the ſame time, <hi>I</hi> will be bold to ſay, that if our <hi>Paroxiſms</hi> cure not in our preſent Circumſtances, we are not only unfortunat, and in imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but are a people moſt undeſerving of our ſignal Mercies received, and may add, in relation to us all, this ſaying in the like caſe, <hi>Lactucas non dandas eſſe hiſce aſinis comedendas, cum illis ſufficiant Cardui. Sed datur locus poenitentiae ſi ſeria videtur converſio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, let us occaſion our own misfortune, as we will, ſure <hi>I</hi> am, a man is honoured with the Character of being Their Majeſties High Commiſſioner, who as he laboured under great Sufferings, ſuſtained great loſſes for his Religious, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Principles, and Countreys ſake, in the later Reigns, was imployed in Negotiations abroad by His preſent Majeſty, to whom both his Integrity and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city was ſufficiently known; and whom, and others (now imployed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government) He conſulted concerning His great and dangerous Interprize, for our Relief: So is a man likewiſe, who with the Noble <hi>Roman,</hi> would upon all occaſions Sacrifice his Life, and Worldly Intereſt for's Religion, King, and Countrey's ſake, and may be intirely Confided in, as one, who to his power, will leave no Stone unturned, to bring our deſireable Things (if we be not the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers of our own good) to ſuch a happy concluſion, as may not only ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat in a general ſatisfaction of all good men; but alſo make every man (who love Peace, unfeigned Truth, and Righteouſneſs) to live in ſafety under his own Vine.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſhould we be Rancountered with ſlights and diſappointments in our Worldly Intereſt, or Promotions, for a Seaſon, <hi>Perinde eſt;</hi> provided our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Religious Rights, <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> be ſecured, which is all we ſeem to pretend to, and not tracing that Heathniſh Immoral Reſolution, <hi>Flectere ſi nequeo ſuperos Acheronta movebo.</hi> For did we propoſe, and elaboratly purſue after great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er things:<note place="margin">Prov. cap. <hi>16.</hi> ver. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> Let us at the ſame time conſider <hi>Solomon's</hi> ſaying, that <hi>tho the lot be caſt into the lap, yet the whole diſpoſing thereof is of the Lord. Et ſi valde quaeſieri, non invenies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>I</hi> preſume (without any Heat, Byaſs, perſonal Prejudice, or privat Intereſt, but in cold Blood) to ſum up all with the <hi>Countrey Man's</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (if not Neceſſary) ſhort <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Exhortation,</hi> to this Sage and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Parliament, Nobility, Gentry, and Burgeſſes, therein Aſſembled, that each of you in ſuch a Critical Juncture, Cure his own weak Side, with the natural <hi>Balm</hi> of <hi>Love, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> (burying all <hi>Heats,</hi> and <hi>Perſonal Prejudice,</hi> laying aſide <hi>Immoderat Zeal,</hi> and <hi>Privat Intereſt,</hi>) to joyn Hand in Hand, to Conſult Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly, Concert Calmly, to Digeſt Wiſely, and to Enact Reſolutely, without any By-ends, ſuch ſolid Laws and Statutes, as may not only Reſtore the Church to its Priſtine Juſt Rights and Priviledges; But alſo may Support It, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ye your ſelves have Devolved upon Their Majeſties, in the firſt place, without Doubts and Fears, and not to leave other Matters undone, in their due Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Which if ye do, and Chriſtianly, Unanimouſly, and Couragiouſly Imploy your ſelves, in your ſeveral Capacities, to promote the Publick Intereſt, and Common Good before your Eyes, the Divine Hand will Aſſiſt you, and you'll not only be called in after Ages, <hi>The Happy and Bleſſed Instruments of Eſtabliſhing the Truth, a Profound and Laſting Peace in the Land;</hi> But alſo, <hi>Your Names will be Recorded to all Poſterity, as the beſt Members, of the beſt Seſſion, of the beſt Parliament, that ever was in</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
